The Iliad Chapters 23 and 24

Chapter 23

Thus they made lamentationlament throughout the city; but the Achaeans, when they were come to the ships and the Hellespont, scattered each man to his own ship; howbeit the Myrmidons would AchillesAchilles nowise suffer to be scattered,
but spake among his war-loving comrades, saying: "Ye Myrmidons of fleet steeds, my trusty comrades, let us not yet loose our single-hooved horses from their cars, but with horses and chariots let us draw nigh and mourn PatroclusPatroclus; for that is the due of the dead.
Then when we have taken our fill of dire lamentinglament, we will unyoke our horses and sup here all together." So spake he, and they raised the voice of wailingpositive all with one accord, and AchillesAchilles was leader thereof. Then thrice about the corpse they drave their fair-maned steedspositive, mourning the while; and among them Thetis roused desire of wailing.
Wetted were the sands and wetted the armour of the warriors with their tears; so mighty a deviser of rout was he for whom they mourned. And among them the son of Peleus was leader in the vehement lamentationlament; laying his man-slaying handspositive upon the breast of his comrade: "Hail, I bid thee, O PatroclusPatroclus, even in the house of HadesGods,
for even now I am bringing to fulfillment all that aforetime I promised thee: that I would drag HectorHector hither and give him raw unto dogs to devour, and of twelve glorious sons of the Trojans would I cut the throats before thy pyre, in my wrath at thy slaying." He spake, and devised foul entreatment for goodly HectorHector,
stretching him on his face in the dust before the bier of the son of Menoetius. And they put off, each man of them, their shining harnesses of bronze, and loosed their loud-neighing horses, and themselves sat down beside the ship of the swift-footed son of Aeacus, a countless host; and he made them a funeral feast to satisfy their hearts.
Many sleek bulls bellowed about the knife, as they were slaughtered, many sheep and bleating goats, and many white-tusked swine, rich with fat, were stretched to singe over the flame of HephaestusGods; and everywhere about the corpse the blood ran so that one might dip cups therein.

But the prince, the swiftfooted son of PeleusAchilles, was led unto goodly AgamemnonAgamemnon by the chiefs of the Achaeans, that had much ado to persuade him thereto, so wroth at heart was he for his comrade. But when, as they went, they were come to the hut of AgamemnonAgamemnon, forthwith they bade clear-voiced heralds
set upon the fire a great cauldron, if so be they might persuade the son of Peleus to wash from him the bloody gore. But he steadfastly denied them, and swore an oath thereto: "Nay, verily by ZeusGods, that is highest and best of gods, it may not be that water should come nigh my head,
until such time as I have laid PatroclusPatroclus on the fire, and have heaped him a barrow, and shorn my hair withal, since never more shall a second grief thus reach my heart, while yet I abide among the living. Howbeit for this present let us yield us to the banquet we needs must loathe; but in the morning rouse thou the folk, king of men AgamemnonAgamemnon,
to bring wood, and to make ready all that it beseemeth a dead man to have, whenso he goeth beneath the murky darkness, to the end that unwearied fire may burn him quickly from sight, and the host betake it to its tasks."
So spake he, and they readily hearkened to him and obeyed,
and speedily making ready each man his meal they supped, nor did thelr hearts lack aught of the equal feast. But when they had put from them the desire of food and drink, they went each man to his hut to take his rest; but the son of Peleus upon the shore of the loud-resounding sea
lay groaning heavily amid the host of the Myrmidons, in an open space where the waves splashed upon the shore. And when sleep seized him, loosenlng the cares of his heart, being shed in sweetness round about him — for sore weary were his glorious limbs with speeding after HectorHector unto windy Ilios—
then there came to him the spirit of hapless PatroclusPatroclus, in all things like his very self, in stature and fair eyes and in voice, and in like raiment was he clad withal; and he stood above AchillesAchilles' head and spake to him, saying:"Thou sleepest, and hast forgotten me, AchillesAchilles.
Not in my life wast thou unmindful of me, but now in my death! Bury me with all speed, that I pass within the gates of HadesGods. Afar do the spirits keep me aloof, the phantoms of men that have done with toils, neither suffer they me to join myself to them beyond the River, but vainly I wander through the wide-gated house of Hades.
And give me thy hand, I pitifully entreat thee, for never more again shall I come back from out of HadesGods, when once ye have given me my due of fire. Never more in life shall we sit apart from our dear comrades and take counsel together, but for me hath loathly fate
opened its maw, the fate that was appointed me even from my birth. Aye, and thou thyself also, AchillesAchilles like to the gods, art doomed to be brought low beneath the wall of the waelthy Trojans. And another thing will I speak, and charge thee, if so be thou wilt hearken. Lay not my bones apart from thine, AchillesAchilles, but let them lie togetherpositive, even as we were reared in your house,
when Menoetius brought me, being yet a little lad, from Opoeis to your country, by reason of grievous man-slaying, on the day when I slew Amphidamus' son in my folly, though I willed it not, in wrathwrath over the dice. Then the knight Peleus received me into his house
and reared me with kindly care and named me thy squire; even so let one coffer enfold our bones, a golden coffer with handles twain, the which thy queenly mother gave thee."
Then in answer spake to him AchillesAchilles, swift of foot:"Wherefore, O head beloved, art thou come hither,
and thus givest me charge about each thing? Nay, verily I will fulfill thee all, and will hearken even as thou biddest. But, I pray thee, draw thou nigher; though it be but for a little space let us clasp our arms one about the other, and take our fill of dire lamenting." So saying he reached forth with his handspositive,
yet clasped him not; but the spirit like a vapour was gone beneath the earth, gibbering faintly. And seized with amazement AchillesAchilles sprang up, and smote his hands together, and spake a word of wailinglament:"Look you now, even in the house of HadesGods is the spirit and phantom somewhat, albeit the mind be not anywise therein;
for the whole night long hath the spirit of hapless PatroclusPatroclus stood over me, weeping and wailingnegative, and gave me charge concerning each thing, and was wondrously like his very self." So spake he, and in them all aroused the desire of lamentlament, and rosy-fingered Dawn shone forth upon them
while yet they wailed around the piteous corpsepositive. But the lord AgamemnonAgamemnon sent forth mules an men from all sides from out the huts to fetch wood and a man of valour watched thereover, even Meriones, squire of kindly Idomeneus. And they went forth bearing in their hands axes for the cutting of wood
and well-woven ropes, and before them went the mules: and ever upward, downward, sideward, and aslant they fared. But when they were come to the spurs of many-fountained Ida, forthwith they set them to fill high-crested oaks with the long-edged bronze in busy haste and with a mighty crash the trees kept falling.
Then the Achaeans split the trunks asunder and bound them behind the mules, and these tore up the earth with their feet as they hasted toward the plain through the thick underbrush. And all the woodcutters bare logs; for so were they bidden of Meriones, squire of kindly Idomeneus.
Then down upon the shore they cast these, man after man, where AchillesAchilles planned a great barrowpositive for PatroclusPatroclus and for himself. But when on all sides they had cast down the measureless wood, they sate them down there and abode, all in one throng. And AchillesAchilles straightway bade the war-loving Myrmidons
gird them about with bronze, and yoke each man his horses to his car. And they arose and did on their armour and mounted their chariots,warriors and charioteers alike. In front fared the men in chariots, and thereafter followed a cloud of footmen, a host past counting and in the midst his comrades bare PatroclusPatroclus.
And as with a garment they wholly covered the corpse with their hairpositive that they shore off and cast thereon; and behind them goodly AchillesAchilles clasped the head, sorrowinglament the while; for peerless was the comrade whom he was speeding to the house of HadesGods.
But when they were come to the place that AchillesAchilles had appointed unto them, they set down the dead, and swiftly heaped up for him abundant store of wood.
Then again swift-footed goodly AchillesAchilles took other counsel; he took his stand apart from the fire and shore off a golden lockpositive, the rich growth whereof he had nursed for the river Spercheüs, and his heart mightily moved, he spake, with a look over the wine-dark sea:"SpercheüsGods, to no purpose did my father Peleus vow to thee
that when I had come home thither to my dear native land, I would shear my hair to thee and offer a holy hecatomb, and on the selfsame spot would sacrifice fifty rams, males without blemish, into thy waters, where is thy demesne and thy fragrant altar. So vowed that old man, but thou didst not fulfill for him his desire.
Now, therefore, seeing I go not home to my dear native land, I would fain give unto the warrior PatroclusPatroclus this lock to fare with him." He spake and set the lock in the hands of his dear comradepositive, and in them all aroused the desire of lamentlament. And now would the light of the sun have gone down upon their weepingpositive,
had not AchillesAchilles drawn nigh to AgamemnonAgamemnon's side and said:"Son of Atreus—for to thy words as to those of none other will the host of the Achaeans give heed— of lamenting they may verily take their fill, but for this present disperse them from the pyre, and bid them make ready their meal; for all things here we to whom the dead is nearest and dearest will take due care;
and with us let the chieftains also abide."
Then when the king of men AgamemnonAgamemnon heard this word, he forthwith dispersed the folk amid the shapely ships, but they that were neareat and dearest to the dead abode there, and heaped up the wood, and made a pyre of an hundred feet this way and that,
and on the topmost part thereof they set the dead manpositive, their hearts sorrow-ladenlament. And many goodly sheep and many sleek kine of shambling gait they flayed and dressed before the pyre; and from them all great-souled AchillesAchilles gathered the fat, and enfolded the dead therein from head to foot, and about him heaped the flayed bodies.
And thereon he set two-handled jars of honey and oil, leaning them against the bier; and four horses with high arched neeks he cast swiftly upon the pyre, groaning aloud the while. Nine dogs had the prince, that fed beneath his table, and of these did AchillesAchilles cut the throats of twain, and cast them upon the pyre.
And twelve valiant sons of the great-souled Trojans slew he with the bronze—and grimanger was the work he purposed in his heart and thereto he set the iron might of fire, to range at large. Then he uttered a groan, and called on his dear comrade by name: "Hail, I bid thee, O PatroclusPatroclus, even in the house of HadesGods,
for now am I bringing all to pass, which afore-time I promised thee. Twelve valiant sons of the great-souled Trojans, lo all these together with thee the flame devoureth; but HectorHector, son of PriamPriam, will I nowise give to the fire to feed upon, but to dogs." So spake he threatening, but with HectorHector might no dogs deal;
nay, the daughter of ZeusGods, AphroditeGods, kept dogs from him by day alike and by night, and with oil anointed she him, rose-sweet, ambrosial, to the end that AchillesAchilles might not tear him as he dragged him. And over him Phoebus ApolloGods drew a dark cloud from heaven to the plain, and covered all the placepositive
whereon the dead man lay, lest ere the time the might of the sun should shrivel his flesh round about on his sinews and limbs.
Howbeit the pyre of dead PatroclusPatroclus kindled not. Then again did swift footed goodlyAchillesAchilles take other counsel; he took his stand apart from the pyre, and made prayer to the two windspositive,
to the North Wind and the West Wind, and promised fair offerings, and full earnestly, as he poured libations from a cup of gold, he besought them to come, to the end that the corpses might speedily blaze with fire, and the wood make haste to be kindled. Then forthwith IrisGods heard his prayer, and hied her with the message to the winds.
They in the house of the fierce-blowing West Wind were feasting all together at the banquet and IrisGods halted from her running on the threshold of stone. Soon as their eyes beheld her, they all sprang up and called her each one to himself. But she refused to sit, and spake saying:
"I may not sit, for I must go back unto the streams of Oceanus, unto the land of the Ethiopians, where they are sacrificing hecatombs to the immortals, that I too may share in the sacred feast. But AchillesGods prayeth the North Wind and the noisy West Wind to come, and promiseth them fair offerings, that so ye may rouse the pyre to burnpositive whereon lieth
PatroclusPatroclus, for whom all the Achaeans groan aloud." When she had thus departed, and they arose with a wondrous din, driving the clouds tumultuously before them. And swiftly they came to the sea to blow thereon, and the wave swelled
beneath the shrill blast; and they came to deep-soiled Troyland, and fell upon the pyre, and mightily roared the wordrous blazing fire. So the whole night long as with one blast they beat upon the flame of the pyrepositive, blowing shrill; and the whole night long swift AchillesAchilles, taking a two-handled cup in hand,
drew wine from a golden howl and poured it upon the earth, and wetted the groundpositive, calling ever upon the spirit of hapless PatroclusPatroclus. As a father waileth for his son, as he burneth his bonespositive, a son newly wed whose death has brought woe to his hapless parents, even so wailedpositive AchillesAchilles for his comrade as he burned his bones,
going heavily about the pyre with ceaseless groaning.
But at the hour when the star of morning goeth forth to herald light over the face of the earth—the star after which followeth saffron-robed Dawn and spreadeth over the sea—even then grew the burning faint, and the flame thereof died down. And the winds went back again to return to their home
over the Thracian sea, and it roared with surging flood. Then the son of PeleusAchilles withdrew apart from the burning pyre, and laid him down sore-wearied; and sweet sleep leapt upon him. But they that were with the son of Atreus gathered in a throng, and the noise and din of their oncoming aroused him;
and he sat upright and spake to them saying:"Son of Atreus, and ye other princes of the hosts of Achaea, first quench ye with flaming wine the burning pyre, even all whereon the might of the fire hath come, and thereafter let us gather the bonespositive of PatroclusPatroclus, Menoetius' son, singling them out well from the rest;
and easy they are to discern, for he lay in the midst of the pyre, while the others burned apart on the edges thereof, horses and men mingled together. Then let us place the bones in a golden urn wrapped in a double layer of fat until such time as I myself be hidden in HadesGods.
Howbeit no huge barrow do I bid you rear with toil for him, but such a one only as beseemeth; but in aftertime do ye Achaeans build it broad and high, ye that shall be left amid the benched ships when I am gone." So spake he, and they hearkened to the swift-footed son of PeleusAchilles.
First they quenched with flaming wine the pyre, so far as the flame had come upon it, and the ash had settled deep; and with weeping they gathered up the white bones of their gentle comrade into a golden urn, and wrapped them in a double layer of fat, and placing the urn in the hut they covered it with a soft linen clothpositive.
Then they traced the compass of the barrow and set forth the foundations thereof round about the pyre, and forthwith they piled the up-piled earth. And when they had piled the barrow, they set them to go back again. But AchillesAchilles stayed the folk even where they were, and made them to sit in a wide gathering; and from his ships brought forth prizes; cauldrons and tripods
and horses and mules and strong oxen and fair-girdled women and grey iron.
For swift charioteers first he set forth goodly prizes, a woman to lead away, one skilled in goodly handiwork, and an eared tripod of two and twenty measures
for him that should be first; and for the second he appointed a mare of six years, unbroken, with a mule foal in her womb; and for the third he set forth a cauldron untouched of fire, a fair cauldron that held four measures, white even as the first; and for the fourth he appointed two talents of gold;
and for the fifth a two-handled urn, yet untouched of fire. Then he stood up, and spake among the Argives, saying: "Son of Atreus, and ye other well-greaved Achaeans, for the charioteers these prizes lie waiting in the lists. If for some other's honour we Achaeans were now holding contests,
surely it were I that should win the first prize, and bear it to my hut; for ye know how far my horses twain surpass in excellence, seeing they are immortal, and it was PoseidonGods that gave them to my father Peleus, and he gave them to me. Howbeit I verily will abide, I and my single-hooved horses,
so valiant and glorious a charioteer have they lost, and one so kind, who full often would pour upon their manes soft soil when he had washed them in bright water. For him they stand and mournpositive, and on the ground their manes are trailing, and the twain stand there, grieving at heart.
But do ye others make yourselves ready throughout the host, whosoever of the Achaeans hath trust in his horses and his jointed car."
So spake the son of PeleusAchilles, and the swift charioteers bestirred them. Upsprang, for the first, Eumelus, king of men, Admetus' dear son, a man well-skilled in horsemanship
and after him upsprang Tydeus' son, mighty Diomedes, and led beneath the yoke the horses of Tros, even them that on a time he had taken from Aeneas, albeit ApolloGods snatched away Aeneas' self; and after him uprose Atreus' son, fair-haired Menelaus, sprung from ZeusGods, and led beneath the yoke swift steeds, Aethe, AgamemnonAgamemnon's mare, and his own horse Podargus.
The mare had Anchises' son Echepolus given to AgamemnonAgamemnon without price, to the end that he might not follow him to windy Ilios, but might abide at home and take his joy; for great wealth had ZeusGods given him, and he dwelt in spaclous Sicyon:
her Menelaus led beneath the yoke, and exceeding fain was she of the race. And fourth Antilochus made ready his fair-maned horses, he the peerless son of Nestor, the king high of heart, the son of Neleus; and bred at Pylos were the swift-footed horses that drew his car. And his father drew nigh and gave counsel
to him for his profit — a wise man to one that himself had knowledge."Antilochus, for all thou art young, yet have ZeusGods and PoseidonGods loved thee and taught thee all manner of horsemanship; wherefore to teach thee is no great need, for thou knowest well how to wheel about the turning-post; yet are thy horses slowest in the race: therefore I deem there will be sorry work for thee. The horses of the others are swifter, but the men know not how to devise more cunning counsel than thine own self. Wherefore come, dear son, lay thou up in thy mind cunning of every sort, to the end that the prizes escape thee not.
By cunning, thou knowest, is a woodman far better than by might; by cunning too doth a helmsman on the wine-dark deep guide aright a swift ship that is buffeted by winds; and by cunning doth charioteer prove better than charioteer.
Another man, trusting in his horses and car,
heedlessly wheeleth wide to this side and that, and his horses roam over the course, neither keepeth he them in hand; whereas he that hath crafty mind, albeit he drive worse horses, keepeth his eye ever on the turning-post and wheeleth close thereby, neither is unmindful how at the first to force his horses with the oxhide reins,
but keepeth them ever in hand, and watcheth the man that leadeth him in the race. Now will I tell thee a manifest sign that will not escape thee. There standeth, as it were a fathom's height above the ground, a dry stump, whether of oak or of pine, which rotteth not in the rain, and two white stones on either side
thereof are firmly set against it at the joinings of the course, and about it is smooth ground for driving. Haply it is a monnment of some man long ago dead, or haply was made the turning-post of a race in days of men of old; and now hath switft-footed goodly AchillesAchilles appointed it his turningpost. Pressing hard thereon do thou drive close thy chariot and horses, and thyself lean in thy well-plaited
car a little to the left of the pair, and to the off horse do thou give the goad, calling to him with a shout, and give him rein from thy hand. But to the post let the near horse draw close, that the nave of the well-wrought wheel seem to graze the surface thereof—
but be thou ware of touching the stone, lest haply thou wound thy horses and wreck thy car; so should there be joy for the rest, but reproach it for thyself. Nay, dear son, be thou wise and on thy guard; for if at the turning-post thou shalt drive past the rest in thy course,
there is no man that shall catch thee by a burst of speed, neither pass thee by, nay, not though in pursuit he were driving goodlyArion, the swift horse of Adrastus, that was of heavenly stock, or those of Laomedon, the goodly breed of this land." So saying Nestor, son of Neleus, sate him down again in his place,
when he had told his son the sum of every matter.
And fifth Meriones made ready his fair-maned horses. Then they mounted their cars, and cast in the lots; and AchillesAchilles shook them, and forth leapt the lot of Nestor's son, Antilochus; after him had the lord Eumelus a place,
and next to him Atreus' son, Menelaus, famed for his spear, and next to him Meriones drew his place; and last of all the son of Tydeus, albeit far the best, drew a place for his chariot. Then took they their places in a row, and AchillesAchilles shewed them the turning-post afar off in the smooth plain; and thereby he set as an umpire
godlike Phoenix, his father's follower, that he might mark the running and tell the truth thereof. Then they all at one moment lifted the lash each above his yoke of horses, and smote them with the reins, and called to them with words, full eagerly and forthwith they sped swiftly over the plain
away from the ships and beneath their breasts the dust arose and stood, as it were a cloud or a whirlwind, and their manes streamed on the blasts of the wind. And the chariots would now course over the bounteous earth, and now again would bound on high; and they that drave
stood in the cars, and each man's heart was athrob as they strove for victory; and they called every man to his horses, that flew in the dust over the plain. But when now the swift horses were fulfilling the last stretch of the course, back toward the grey sea, then verily was made manifest the worth of each,
and the pace of their horses was forced to the uttermost. And forthwith the swift-footed mares of the son of Pheres shot to the front, and after them Diomedes' stallions of the breed of Tros; not far behind were they, but close behind, for they seemed ever like to mount upon
Eumelus' car, and with their breath his back waxed warm and his broad shoulders, for right over him did they lean their heads as they flew along. And now would Tydeus' son have passed him by or left the issue in doubt, had not Phoebus Apollo waxed wroth with him and smitten from his hand the shining lash.
Then from his eyes ran tears in his wrathwrath for that he saw the mares coursing even far swiftlier still than before, while his own horses were hampered, as running without goad.
But Athene was not unaware of Apollo's cheating of the son of Tydeus, and right swiftly sped she after the shepherd of the host,
and gave him back the lash and put strength into his horses. Then in wrath was she gone after the son of Admetus, and the goddess brake the yoke of his steeds, and to his cost the mares swerved to this side and that of the course, and the pole was swung to the earth; and Eumelus himself was hurled from out the car beside the wheel,
and from his elbows and his mouth and nose the skin was stripped, and his forehead above his brows was bruised; and both his eyes were filled with tears and the flow of his voice was checked. Then Tydeus' son turned his single-hooved horses aside and drave on, darting out far in advance of the rest; for Athene
put strength in his horses and gave glory to himself. And after him drave the son of Atreus, fair-haired Menelaus. But Antilochus called to the horses of his father:"Go in now, ye twain as well; strain to your utmost speed. With yon steeds verily I nowise bid you strive,
with the horses of wise-hearted Tydeus to the which Athene hath now given speed and vouchsafed glory to him that driveth them. But the horses of the son of Atreus do ye overtake with speed, and be not outstripped of them, lest shame be shed on you by Aethe that is but a mare. Why are ye outstripped, good steeds?
For thus will I speak out to you, and verily it shall be brought to pass: no tendance shall there be for you twain with Nestor, the shepherd of the host, but forthwith will he slay you with the sharp bronze, if through your heedlessness we win but a worse prize. Nay, have after them with all speed ye may,
and this will I myself contrive and plan, that we slip past them in the narrow way; it shall not escape me." So spake he, and they, seized with fear at the rebuke of their master, ran swiftlier on for a little time, and then quickly did Antilochus, staunch in fight, espy a narrow place in the hollow road.
A rift there was in the ground, where the water, swollen by winter rains, had broken away a part of the road and had hollowed all the place. There drave Menelaus in hope that none other might drive abreast of him. But Antilochus turned aside his single-hooved horses, and drave on outside the track, and followed after him, a little at one side.
And the son of Atreus was seized with fear, and shouted to Antilochus: "Antilochus, thou art driving recklessly; nay, rein in thy horses! Here is the way straitened, but presently it will be wider for passing; lest haply thou work harm to us both by fouling my car."
So spake he, but Antilochus drave on even the more hotly,
and plied the goad, as he were one that heard not. And far is the range of a discus swung from the shoulder, which a young man hurleth, making trial of his strength, even so far ran they on; but the mares of the son of Atreus gave back, for of his own will he forbare to urge them,
lest haply the single-hooved horses should clash together in the track, and overturn the well-plaited cars, and themselves be hurled in the dust in their eager haste for victory. Then fair-haired Menelaus chid Antilochus, and said:"Antilochus, than thou is none other of mortals more malicious.
Go, and perdition take thee, since falsely did we Achaeans deem thee wise. Howbeit even so shalt thou not bear off the prize without an oath." So said he, and called to his horses, saying: "Hold not back, I bid you, neither stand ye still with grieflament at heart. Their feet and knees will grow weary
before yours, for they both are lacking in youth." So spake be, and they, seized with fear at the rebuke of their master, ran swiftlier on, and quickly came close anigh the others. But the Argives sitting in the place of gathering were gazing at the horses, that flew amid the dust over the plain.
And the first to mark them was Idomeneus, leader of the Cretans, for he sat without the gathering, the highest of all, in a place of outlook, and when he heard the voice of him that shouted, albeit afar off, he knew it; and he was ware of a horse, shewing clear to view in front, one that was a bay all the rest of him, but on his forehead was
a white spot round like the moon. And he stood up, and spake among the Argives saying:"My friends, leaders and rulers of the Argives, is it I alone that discern the horses, or do ye as well? Other are they, meseemeth, that be now in front,
and other is the charioteer that appeareth; and the mares will have come to harm out yonder on the plain, they that were in front on the outward course. For in truth I marked them sweeping first about the turning-post, but now can I nowhere spy them, though mine eyes glance everywhither over the Trojan plain, as I gaze.
Did the reins haply slip from the charioteer, and was he unable to guide the course aright about the post, and did he fail in the turn? Even there, methinks, must he have been hurled to earth, and have wrecked his car, and the mares must have swerved from the course in wild terror of heart. Howbeit stand ye up also, and look; for myself
I discern not clearly, but the man seemeth to me to be an Aetolian by race, and is king among the Argives, even the son of horse-taming Tydeus, mighty Diomedes."
Then shamefully chid him swift Aias, son of Oïleus:"Idomeneus, why art thou a braggart from of old? Nay, still afar off are
the high-stepping mares speeding over the wide plain. Neither art thou so far the youngest among the Argives, nor do thine eyes look forth from thy head so far the keenliest yet thou ever pratest loudly. It beseemeth thee not to be loud of speech, for here be others better than thou.
The selfsame mares are in the lead, that led of old, even they of Eumelus, and himself he standeth firmly in the car and holdeth the reins." Then the leader of the Cretans waxed wroth, and spake in answer:"Aias, thou master of railing, witless in counsel, in all things else thou fallest behind the other Argives, for thy mind is stubborn.
Come now, let us wager a tripod or a cauldron, and as umpire betwixt us twain let us choose Atreus' son AgamemnonAgamemnon, as to which mares are in the lead — that thou mayst learn by paying the price." So spake he, and forthwith uprose in wrath swift Aias, son of Oïleus, to answer him with angry words;
and yet furthur would the strife between the twain have gone, had not AchillesAchilles himself stood up, and spoken, saying:"No longer now, O Aias and Idomeneus, answer ye one another with angry words, with evil words, for that were unseemly. Ye have indignation with another, whoso should act thus.
Nay, sit ye down in the place of gathering, and watch ye the horses; full soon in their eager haste for victory will they come hither, and then shall ye know, each man of you, the horses of the Argives, which be behind, and which in the lead." So spake he, and Tydeus' son came hard anigh as he drave,
and with his lash dealt many a stroke down from the shoulder; and his horses leapt on high as they swiftly sped on their way. And ever did flakes of dust smite the charioteer, and his chariot overlaid with gold and tin ran on behind the swift-footed horses, and small trace there was
of the wheel tires behind in the light dust, as the twain flew speeding on. Then he drew up in the midst of the place of gathering, and in streams the sweat flowed from the necks and chests of the horses to the ground. And Diomedes himself leapt to the ground from his gleaming car,
and leaned the goad against the yoke. Neither did mighty Sthenelus anywise tarry, but speedily took the prize, and gave to his comrades, high of heart, the woman and the eared tripod to bear away; and himself loosed the horses from beneath the yoke.
And next after him Antilochus of the stock of Neleus drave his horses,
for that by guile, and nowise by speed, had he outstripped Menelaus; howbeit even so Menelaus guided his swift horses close behind. Far as a horse is from the wheel, a horse that draweth his master over the plain,and straineth at the car—the tire thereof do the hindmost hairs of his tail touch,
for it runneth close behind, and but scant space is there between, as he courseth over the wide plain—even by so much was Menelaus behind peerless Antilochus, though at the first he was behind far as a man hurleth the discus; howbeit quickly was he overtaking Antilochus, for the goodly mettle
of the mare of AgamemnonAgamemnon, fair-maned Aethe, waxed ever higher. And if the course had been yet longer for the twain, then had he passed him by, neither left the issue in doubt. But Meriones, valiant squire of Idomeneus, was a spear-cast behind glorious Menelaus,
for slowest of all were his fair-maned horses, and himself least skilled to drive a chariot in the race. And the son of Admetus came in last, behind all the rest, dragging his fair chariotpositive and driving his horses before him. And at sight of him swift-footed, goodly AchillesAchilles had pitylament
and he stood uppositive amid the Argives, and spake winged wordspositive: "Lo, in the last place driveth his single-hooved horses the man that is far the best. But come, let us give him a prize, as is meet, a prize for the second place; but the first let the son of Tydeus bear away." So spake he, and they all assentedpositive even as he bade.
And now would he have given him the mare —for the Achaeans assented thereto —but that Antilochus, son of great-souled Nestor, uprose and answered Achilles, son of PeleusAchilles, to claim his due: "AchillesAchilles, sore wroth shall I bewrath with thee if thou fulfill this word, for thou art minded to rob menegative of my prize,
bethinking thee of this, how his chariot and his swift honses came to harm, and himself withal, good man though he be. Nay, he should have made prayer to the immortals, then had he nowise come in last of all in the race.negative But if so be thou pitiest himlament, and he be dear to thy heart, lo, in thy hut is great store of gold, and bronze is there
and sheep, aye, and handmaids too, and single-hooved horses. Thereof do thou hereafter take and give him even a goodlier prize, or even now forthwith, that the Achaeans may applaud thee. But the mare will not yield; for her let any man that will, essay to do battle with me by might of hand."

So spake he, and swift-footed, goodly AchillesAchilles smiled, having joyrelief in Antilochus, for that he was his dear comrade; and he made answer, and spake to him winged wordspositive:"Antilochus, if thou wilt have men give to Eumelus some other thing from out my house as a further prize, even this will I do.
I will give him the corselet that I took from Asteropaeus; of bronze is it, and thereon is set in circles a casting of bright tin, and it shall be to him a thing of great worth." He spake, and bade his dear comradepositive Automedon bring it from the hut and he went and brought itpositive,
and placed it in Eumelus' hands and he received it gladly.positive Then among them uprose also Menelaus, sore vexed at heart, furiously wroth at Antilochus; and a herald gave the staff into his hand, and proclaimed silence among the Argives; and thereafter spake among them the godlike man:negative
"Antilochus, thou that aforetime wast wise, what a thing hast thou wrought! Thou hast put my skill to shame and hast thwarted my horses, thrusting to the front thine own that were worser far. Come now, ye leaders and rulers of the Argives, judge ye aright betwixt us twain, neither have regard unto either,
lest in aftertime some one of the brazen-coated Achaeans shall say: ‘Over Antilochus did Menelaus prevail by lies, and depart with the mare, for that his horses were worser far, but himself the mightier in worth and in power.’ Nay, but I will myself declare the right, and I deem that
none other of the Danaans shall reproach me, for my judgement shall be just. Antilochus, fostered of ZeusGods, up, come thou hither and, as is the appointed way, stand thou before thy horses and chariot, and take in hand the slender lash with which aforetimethou wast wont to drive, and laying thy hand on thy horses swear by him that holdeth and shaketh the earth
that not of thine own will didst thou hinder my chariot by guile."
Then in turn wise Antilochus answered him:positive "Bear with me, now, for far younger am I than thou, king Menelaus, and thou art the elder and the better man. Thou knowest of what sort are the transgressions of a man that he is young,
for hasty is he of purpose and but slender is his wit. Wherefore let thy heart be patient; the mare that I have won will I give thee of my self. Aye, and if thou shouldst ask some other goodlier thing from out my house, forthwith were I fain to give it thee out of hand, rather than all my days be cast out of thy heart, thou nurtured of ZeusGods,
and be a sinner in the eyes of the gods." So spake the son of great-souled Nestor, and led up the mare, and gave her into the hands of Menelaus.positive And his heart was gladdenedrelief even as the corn when with the dew upon the ears it waxeth ripe, what time the fields are bristling.
In such wise, Menelaus, was thy heart gladdened in thy breast. Then he spake winged words unto Antilochospositive, saying: "Antilochus, lo now, I of myself cease from mine anger against thee, since nowise flighty or light of wit wast thou of old, albeit now hath thy youth got the better of thy reason.
Another time seek not to outwit thy betters. Verily not soon should another of the Achaeans have persuaded me, but thou hast suffered greatly and toiled greatly, thou and thy brave father and thy brother, for my sake; wherefore I will hearken to thy prayer, aye,
and will give unto thee the mare, for all she is mine own, to the end that these too may know that my heart is never over-haughty neither unbending." He spake, and gave the mare unto Nosmonpositive, the comrade of Antilochus, to lead away, and himself thereafter took the shining cauldronpositive. And Meriones took up the two talents of goldpositive in the fourth place,
even as he drave; but the fifth prize was left unclaimed, even the two-handled urn. Unto Nestor Achilles gave thispositive, bearing it through the gathering of the Argives; and he came to his side, and saidpositive"Take this now, old sire, and let it be treasure for thee, a memorial of Patroclus' burying; for nevermore shalt thou behold him
among the Argives. Lo, I give thee this prize unwon; for not in boxing shalt thou contend, neither in wrestling, nor shalt thou enter the lists for the casting of javelins, neither run upon thy feet; for now grievous old age weigheth heavy upon thee."
So saying he placed the urn in his armspositive, and Nestor received it gladlypositive,
and spake, and addressed him with winged wordspositive :"Aye, verily, my son, all this hast thou spoken aright, for my limbs, even my feet, are no more firm, O my friend, as of old, nor do my arms as of old dart out lightly from my shoulders on either side. Would that I were young, and my strength were firm
as on the day when the Epeians were burying lord Amarynceus at Buprasium, and his sons appointed prizes in honour of the king. Then was there no man that proved himself my peer, neither of the Epeians nor of Pylians themselves nor of the great-souled Aetolians. In boxing I overcame Clytomedes, son of Enops,
and in wrestling Ancaeus of Pleuron, who stood up against me; Iphiclus I outran in the foot-race, good man though he was; and in casting the spear I outthrew Phyleus and Polydorus. In the chariot race alone the twain sons of Actor outstripped me by force of numbers crowding their horses to the front, being exceeding jealous for victory,
for that the goodliest prize abode yet there in the lists. Twin brethren were they— the one drave with sure hand, drave with sure hand, while the other plied the goad. Thus was I on a time, but now let men that be younger face such-like tasks; me it behoveth to yield to grievous old age,
but then was I pre-eminent among warriors. But come, for thy comrade too hold thou funeral rites with contests. For this gift, I receive it wlth gladness, and my heart rejoiceth that thou rememberest me, thy friend, neither am I forgotten of thee, and the honour wherewith it beseemeth that I be honoured among the Achaeans.positive
And to thee may the gods in requital thereof grant grace to satisfy thy heart." So spake he, and the son of PeleusAchilles went his way through the great throng of the Achaeans, when he had hearkened to all the praisepositive of the son of Neleus. Then set he forth prizespositive for grievous boxing. A sturdy mule he brought and tethered in the place of gathering,
a mule of six years, unbroken, the which is hardest of all to break; and for him that should be worsted he appointed a two-handled cup. Then he stood up, and spake among the Argives, saying: "Son of Atreus, and ye other well-greaved Achaeans, for these prizes we invite warriors twain, the best there are, to lift up their hands and box amain.positive
Let him to whom ApolloGods shall grant strength to endure, and all the Achaeans have knowledge thereof, go his way to his hut leading the sturdy muIe; but he that is worsted shall bear as his prize the two-handled cup."
So spake he, and forthwith uprose a man valiant and tallpositive,
well-skilled in boxing, even Epeius, son of Panopeus; and he laid hold of the sturdy mule, and spake,negative saying:"Let him draw nigh, whoso is to bear as his prize the two-handled cup : the mule I deem that none other of the Achaeans shall lead away, by worsting me with his fists, for I avow me to be the best man.
Sufficeth it not that I fall short in battle? One may not, meseemeth, prove him a man of skill in every work. For thus will I speak, and verily this thing shall be brought to pass : utterly will I rend his flesh and crush his bones.negative Wherefore let them that be next of kin abide here in a throng,
that they may bear him forth when worsted by my hands." So spake he, and they all became hushed in silence.negative Euryalus alone uprose to face himpositive, a godlike man, son of king Mecisteus, son of Talaus, who on a time had come to Thebes for the burial of Oedipus,
when he had fallen, and there had worsted all the sons of Cadmus. And Tydeus' son, famed for his spear, made Euryalus ready, heartening him with words, and much he wished for him victory.positive A girdle first he cast about him, and thereafter gave him well-cut thongs of the hide of an ox of the field.
So the twain, when they had girded themselves, stepped into the midst of the place of gathering, and lifting their mighty hands on high one against the other, fell to, and their hands clashed together in heavy blows. Dread then was the grinding of their teeth, and the sweat flowed on every side from off their limbspositive But upon him goodly Epeius rushedpositive
as he peered for an opening,and smote him on the cheek, nor after that, methinks, did he long stand upright, for even there did his glorious limbs sink beneath himpositive. And as when beneath the ripple of the North Wind a fish leapeth up on the tangle-strewn sand of a shallow, and then the black wave hideth it, even so leapt up Euryalus when he was smittenpositive. But great-souled Epeius
took him in his hands and set him on his feet, and his dear comrades thronged about him and led him through the place of gathering with trailing feet, spitting out clotted blood and letting his head hang to one side; and they brought him wandering in his wits and set him down in the midst of their company, and themselves went and fetched the two-handled cup.positive

Then the son of Peleus forthwith ordained in the sight of the Danaans other prizes for a third contest, even for toilsome wrestlingpositive — for him that should win, a great tripod to stand upon the fire, that the Achaeans prized amongst them at the worth of twelve oxen; and for him that should be worsted he set in the midst a woman
of manifold skill in handiwork, and they prized her at the worth of four oxen. And he stood up and spake among the Argives sayingpositive:"Up now, ye twain that will make essay likewise in this contest." So spake he, and thereat arose great Telamonian Aias, and up stood Odysseus of many wiles, he of guileful mind.positive
Then the twain, when they had girded themselves, stepped into the midst of the place of gathering, and laid hold each of the other in close grip with their mighty hands, even as the gable-rafters of a high house, which some famous craftsman joineth together, that he may have shelter from the might of the winds.positive And their backs creaked beneath the violent tugging of bold handspositive,
and the sweat flowed down in streams; and many a weal, red with blood, sprang up along their ribs and shoulders; and ever they strove amain for victory, to win the fashioned tripod.positive Neither might Odysseus avail to trip Aias and throw him to the ground,
nor Aias him, for the mighty strength of Odysseus held firm.positive But when at the last they were like to weary the well-greaved Achaeans, then unto Odysseus spake great Telamonian Aias, sayingpositive:"Zeus-born, son of Laertes, Odysseus of many wiles, lift thou me, or let me lift thee; but the issue shall rest with ZeusGods."
He spake, and lifted him; but Odysseus forgat not his guile. He smote with a sure blow the hollow of Aias' knee from behind, and loosed his limbs, so that he was thrown backward, and Odysseus fell upon his chest; and the people gazed thereon and were seized with wonder.positive Then in his turn the much-enduring goodly Odysseus essayed to lift,
and moved him a little from the ground, but lifted him not, howbeit he crooked his knee within that of Aias, and upon the ground the twain fell one hard by the other, and were befouled with dust. And now would they have sprung up again for the third time and have wrestled,positive but that AchillesAchilles himself uprose, and held them backpositive:
"No longer strain ye now, neither be worn with pain. Victory is with you both; take then equa1 prizes and go your ways, that other Achaeans too may strive." So spake he, and they readily hearkened to him and obeyed, and wiping from their bodies the dust they put upon them their tunics.positive

Then the son of PeleusAchilles straightway set forth other prizespositive for fleetness of foot: a mixingbowl of silver, richly wrought; six measures it held, and in beauty it was far the goodliest in all the earth, seeing that Sidonians, well skilled in deft handiwork, had wrought it cunningly, and men of the Phoenicians brought it over the murky deep, and landed it in harbour,
and gave it as a gift to Thoas; and as a ransom for Lycaon, son of PriamPriam, Jason's son Euneos gave it to the warrior PatroclusPatroclus. This bowl did AchillesAchilles set forth as a prize in honour of his comradepositive, even for him whoso should prove fleetest in speed of foot.
For the second again he set an ox great and rich with fat; and a half-talent in gold he appointed for the last.positive And he stood up, and spake among the Argives sayingpositive: "Up now, ye that will make essay likewise in this contest." So spake he, and forthwith uprosepositive swift Aias, son of Oïleus,
and Odysseus of many wiles, and after them Antilochus, Nestor's son, for he surpassed all the youths in swiftness of foot. Then took they their places in a row, and Achilles showed them the goal, and a course was marked out for them from the turning-point.positive Then speedily the son of Oïleus forged to the front, and close after him sped goodly Odysseuspositive;
close as is the weaving-rod to the breast of a fair-girdled woman, when she deftly draweth it in her hands, pulling the spool past the warp, and holdeth the rod nigh to her breast; even so close behind ran Odysseus,
and his feet trod in the footsteps of Aias or ever the dust had settled therein, and down upon his head beat the breath of goodly Odysseus, as he ran ever swiftly on; and all the Achaeans shouted to further him as he struggled for victory, and called to him as he strained to the utmost.positive But when now they were running the last part of the course, straightway Odysseus made prayer in his heartpositive to flashing-eyed AtheneGods:
"Hear me, goddess, and come a goodly helper to my feet." So spake he in prayer, and Pallas AtheneGods heard him, and made his limbs light, his feet and his hands abovepositive. But when they were now about to dart forth to win the prize, then Aias slipped as he rannegative—for AtheneGods hampered himnegative—
where was strewn the filth from the slaying of the loud bellowing bulls that swift-footed AchillesAchilles had slain in honour of PatroclusPatroclus; and with the filth of the bulls were his mouth and nostrils fillednegative. So then much-enduring, goodly Odysseus took up the bowl, seeing he came in the firstpositive, and glorious Aias took the ox.positive
And he stood holding in his hands the horn of the ox of the field, spewing forth the filthnegative; and he spake among the Argivespositive: "Out upon it, lo, the goddess hampered me in my runningnegative, she that standeth ever by Odysseus' side like a mother, and helpeth him."
So spake he, but they all laughed merrily at him.positive
Then Antilochus bare away the last prize, smiling the while, and spake among the Argives, sayingpositive: "Among you all that know it well, will I declare, my friends, that even to this day the immortals shew honour to older men.positive For Aias is but a little older than I,
whereas Odysseus is of an earlier generation and of earlier men—a green old age is his, men say—yet hard were he for any other Achaean to contend with in running, save only for Achilles." So spake he, and gave glorypositive to the son of Peleus, swift of foot.Achilles And AchillesAchilles made answer, and spake to him, sayingpositive:
"Antilochus, not in vain shall thy word of praise be spoken; nay, I will add to thy prize a half-talent of goldpositive." So saying, he set it in his hands, and Antilochus received it gladlypositive. But the son of PeleusAchilles brought and set in the placepositive of gathering a far-shadowing spear, and therewith a shield and helmet,
the battlegear of Sarpedon, that PatroclusPatroclus stripped from him; and he stood up, and spake among the Argives, saying:"To win these prizes invite we warriors twain, the best there are, to clothe them in their armour and take bronze that cleaveth the flesh, and so make trial each of the other before the host.
Whoso of the twain shall first reach the other's fair flesh, and touch the inward parts through armour and dark blood, to him will I give this silver-studded swordpositive—a goodly Thracian sword which I took from Asteropaeus; and these arms let the twain bear away to hold in common;
and a goodly banquet shall we set before them in our huts." So spake he, and thereat arose great Telamonian Aias, and up rose the son of Tydeus, stalwart Diomedespositive. So when they had armed them on either side of the throng, into the midst strode the twain, eager for battlepositive,
glaring terribly; and amazement held all the Achaeans. But when they were come near as they advance done against the other, thrice they set upon each other, and thrice they clashed togetherpositive. Then Aias thrust upon the shieldpositive, that was well-balanced upon every side, but reached not the flesh, for the corselet within kept off the spear.
But Tydeus' son over the great shield sought ever to reach the neck with the point of his shining spearnegative, Then verily the Achaeans, seized with fear for Aias, bade them cease and take up equal prizespositive. Howbeit to Tydeus' son the warrior gave the great sword,
bringing it with its scabbard and its well-cut baldric.
Then the son of PeleusAchilles set forth a mass of rough-cast ironpositive, which of old the mighty strength of Eëtion was wont to hurl; but him had swift-footed goodly AchillesAchilles slain, and bare this away on his ships with his other possessions.
And he stood up, and spake among the Argivespositive, saying :"Up now, ye that will make essay likewise in this contest. Though his rich fields lie very far remote, the winner hereof will have it five revolving years to serve his needpositive; for not through lack of iron will his shepherd or ploughman
fare to the city; nay, this will supply them." So spake he, and thereat arose Polypoetes, staunch in fight, and the mighty strength of godlike Leonteus, and Aias, son of Telamon, and goodly Epeius.positive Then they took their places in orderpositive, and goodly Epeius grasped the mass,
and whirled and flung itpositive; and all the Achaeans laughed aloudnegative thereat. Then in turn Leonteus, scion of Ares, made a castpositive; and thirdly great Telamonian Aias hurled it from his strong hand, and sent it past the marks of allpositive. But when Polypoetes, staunch in fight,
grasped the mass, far as a herdsman flings his crook, and it flieth whirling over the herds of kine, even so far cast he it beyond all the gathering; and the folk shouted aloud. And the comrades of strong Polypoetes rose up and bare to the hollow ships the prize of the king.positive
Then for the archers he set forth as a prize dark iron—ten double axes laid he down, and ten single; and he set up the mast of a dark-prowed ship far off in the sands, and with a slender cord made fast thereto by the foot a timorous dove, and bade shoot thereat.positive
"Whoso shall hit the timorous dove let him take up all the double axes and bear them home, and whoso shall hit the cord, albeit he miss the bird: lo, his is the worser shot; he shall bear as his prize the single axes.positive"
So spake he, and there arosepositive the might of the prince Teucer,
and Meriones the valiant squire of Idomeneus. Then took they the lots and shook them in a helmet of bronze, and Teucer drew by lot the first place. Forthwith he let fly an arrow with might, howbeit he vowed not that he would sacrifice to the king a glorious hecatomb of firstling lambs.positive
So he missed the birdnegative, for ApolloGods grudged himanger that, but hit the cord beside its foot wherewith the bird was tied, and clean away the bitter arrow cut the cord. Then the dove darted skyward, and the cord hung loose toward earth;positive and the Achaeans shouted aloudpositive.
But Meriones speedily snatched the bow from Teucer's hand—an arrow had he long been holding while Teucer aimednegative—and vowed forthwith that he would sacrificenegative to ApolloGods that smiteth afar a glorious hecatomb of firstling lambs. High up beneath the cloud he spied the timorous dovenegative;
there as she circled round he struck her in the midst beneath the wing, and clean through passed the shaft, and fell again and fixed itself in the ground before the foot of Meriones; but the dove, lighting on the mast of the dark-prowed ship, hung down her head, and her thick plumage drooped.negative
Swiftly the life fled from her limbs, and she fell far from the mast; and the people gazed thereon and were seized with wonder.negative And Meriones took up all ten double axes, and Teucer bare the single to the hollow ships.positive Then the son of PeleusAchilles brought and set in the place of gathering a far-shadowing spearpositive
and a cauldron, that the fire had not yet touched, of an ox's worth, embossed with flowers; and men that were hurlers of javelins arose. Up rose the son of Atreus, wide-ruling AgamemnonAgamemnon and Meriones, the valiant squire of Idomeneus. But among them spake swift-footed, goodly AchillesAchilles:
"Son of Atreus, we know how far thou excellest all, and how far thou art the best in might and in the casting of the spear; nay, take thou this prize and go thy way to the hollow ships; but the spear let us give to the warrior Meriones,positive if thy heart consenteth thereto: so at least would I have it:"
So spake he, and the king of men, AgamemnonAgamemnon, failed not to hearken. Then to Meriones he gave the spear of bronze, but the warrior handed to the herald Talthybius the beauteous prize.positive
Then was the gathering broken up, and the folk scattered, each man to go to his own ship. The rest bethought them of supper and of sweet sleep, to take their fill thereofpositive; but AchillesAchilles wept, ever remembering his dear comradenegative, neither might sleep,
that mastereth all, lay hold of him, but he turned him ever to this side or to that, yearning for the man-hood and valorous mightlament of PatroclusPatroclus, thinking on all he had wrought with him and all the woes he had borne, passing though wars of men and the grievous waves. Thinking thereon he would shed big tearsnegative,
lying now upon his side, now upon his back, and now upon his face; and then again he would rise upon his feet and roam distraught along the shore of the sea.negative Neither would he fail to mark the Dawn, as she shone over the sea and the sea-beaches, but would yoke beneath the car his swift horses,
and bind HectorHector behind the chariot to drag him withal; and when he had haled him thrice about the barrow of the dead son of Menoetiusnegative, he would rest again in his hut, but would leave HectorHector outstretched on his face in the dust. Howbeit ApolloGods kept all defacement from his flesh, pitying the warriorpositive
even in death, and with the golden aegis he covered him wholly, that AchillesAchilles might not tear his body as he dragged him.
Thus AchillesAchilles in his furywrath did foul despite unto goodly HectorHector; but the blessed gods had pity on him as they beheld him, and bestirred the keen-sighted Argeiphontes to steal away the corpse.
And the thing was pleasing unto all the rest, yet not unto HeraGods or PoseidonGods or the flashing-eyed maiden, but they continued even as when at the first sacred Ilios became hateful in their eyes and PriamPriam and his folk, by reason of the sin of Alexander, for that he put reproach upon those goddesses when they came to his steading,
and gave precedence to her who furthered his fatal lustfulness.negative But when at length the twelfth morn thereafter was come, then among the immortals spakepositive Phoebus ApolloGods:"Cruel are ye, O ye gods, and workers of bane. Hath HectorHector then never burned for you thighs of bulls and goats without blemish?
Him now have ye not the heart to save, a corpse though he be, for his wife to look upon and his mother and his child, and his father PriamPriam and his people, who would forthwith burn him in the fire and pay him funeral rites. Nay, it is the ruthless AchillesAchilles, O ye gods, that ye are fain to succour,
him whose mind is nowise right, neither the purpose in his breast one that may be bent; but his heart is set on cruelty,anger even as a lion that at the bidding of his great might and lordly spirit goeth forth against the flocks of men to win him a feast; even so hath AchillesAchilles lost all pity, neither is shame in his heart,
the which harmeth men greatly and profiteth them withal. Lo, it may be that a man hath lost one dearer even than was this—a brother, that the selfsame mother bare, or haply a son; yet verily when he hath wept and wailed for him he maketh an end; for an enduring soul have the Fates given unto men.
But this man, when he hath reft goodly HectorHector of life, bindeth him behind his chariot and draggeth him about the barrow of his dear comrade; in sooth neither honour nor profit shall he have therefrom. Let him beware lest we wax wroth with him, good man though he be; for lo, in his fury he doth foul despite unto senseless clay."
Then stirred to angeranger spake to him white-armed HeraGods:"Even this might be as thou sayest, Lord of the silver bow, if indeed ye gods will vouchsafe like honour to AchillesAchilles and to HectorHector. HectorHector is but mortal and was suckled at a woman's breast, but AchillesAchilles is the child of a goddess that I mine own self
fostered and reared, and gave to a warrior to be his wife, even to Peleus, who was heartily dear to the immortals. And all of you, O ye gods, came to her marriage, and among them thyself too didst sit at the feast, thy lyre in thy hand, O thou friend of evil-doers, faithless ever."
Then Zeus, the cloud-gatherer,Gods answered hernegative, and said:
"HeraGods, be not thou utterly wroth against the gods; the honour of these twain shall not be as one; howbeit HectorHector too was dearest to the gods of all mortals that are in Ilios. So was he to me at least, for nowise failed he of acceptable gifts. For never was my altar in lack of the equal feast,
the drink-offiering and the savour of burnt-offering, even the worship that is our due. Howbeit of the stealing away of bold HectorHector will we naught; it may not be but that AchillesAchilles would be ware thereof; for verily his mother cometh ever to his side alike by night and day. But I would that one of the gods would call Thetis to come unto me,
that I may speak to her a word of wisdom, to the end that AchillesAchilles may accept gifts from PriamPriam, and give HectorHector back." So spake he, and storm-footed Iris hasted to bear his messagepositive, and midway between Samos and rugged Imbros she leapt into the dark sea, and the waters sounded loud above her.
Down sped she to the depths hike a plummet of lead, the which, set upon the horn of an ox of the field, goeth down bearing death to the ravenous fishes. And she found Thetis in the hollow cave, and round about her other goddesses of the sea sat in a throng, and she in their midst
was wailing for the fate of her peerless son, who to her sorrow was to perish in deep-soiled Troy, far from his native land. And swift-footed Iris drew near, and spake to her:"Rouse thee, 0 Thetis; ZeusGods, whose counsels are everlasting, calleth thee." Then spake in answer Thetis, the silver-footed goddess:
"Wherefore summoneth me that mighty god? I have shame to mingle in the company of the immortals, seeing I have measurehess griefs at heart. Howbeit I will go, neither shall his word be vain, whatsoever he shall speak."
So saying, the fair goddess took a dark-hued veil, than which was no raiment more black,
and set out to go, and before her wind-footed swift Iris led the waypositive; and about them the surge of the sea parted asunder. And when they had stepped forth upon the beach they sped unto heaven; and they found the son of Cronos, whose voice is borne afar, and around him sat gathered together all the other blessed gods that are for ever.
Then she sate her down beside father ZeusGods, and AtheneGods gave place. And HeraGods set in her hand a fair golden cup, and spake words of cheer.; and Thetis drank, and gave back the cup. Then among them the father of men and gods was first to speakpositive:"Thou art come to Olympus, 0, goddess Thetis,
for all thy sorrow, though thou hast comfortless grief at heart; I know it of myself; yet even so will I tell thee wherefore I called thee hither. For nine days' space hath strife arisen among the immortals as touching the corpse of HectorHector and Achilles, sacker of citiesAchilles. They are for bestirring the keen-sighted Argeiphontes to steal the body away,
yet herein do I accord honour unto AchillesAchilles; for I would fain keep in time to come thy worship and thy love. Haste thee with all speed to the host and declare unto thy son my bidding. Say unto him that the gods are angered with himnegative, and that I above all immortals am filled with wrathwrath, for that in the fury of his heart
he holdeth HectorHector at the beaked ships and gave him not back, if so be he may be seized with fear of me and give HectorHector back. But I will send forth Iris unto great-hearted PriamPriam, to bid him go to the ships of the Achaeans to ransom his dear son, and to bear giftspositive unto AchillesAchilles which shall make glad his heart."

So spake he, and the goddess, silver-footed Thetis, failed not to hearken, but went darting down from the peaks of Olympus, and came to the hut of her son.positive There she found him groaning ceaselesslynegative, and round about him his dear comrades with busy haste were making ready their early meal,
and in the hut a ram, great and shaggy, lay slaughtered for them. Then she,his queenly mother, sate her down close by his side and stroked him with her hand, and spake, and called him by namepositive:"My child, how long wilt thou devour thine heart with weeping and sorrowing, and wilt take no thought of food,
neither of the couch? Good were it for thee even to have dalliance in a woman's embrace. For, I tell thee, thou shalt not thyself be long in life, but even now doth death stand hard by thee and mighty fate. But hearken thou forthwith unto me, for I am a messenger unto thee from Zeus. He declareth that that the gods are angered with theeanger,
and that himself above all immortals is filled with wrathwrath, for that in the fury of thine heart thou holdest HectorHector at the beaked ships, and gavest him not back. Nay come, give him up, and take ransom for the dead." Then in answer to her spake Achilles, swift of footAchilles: "So let it be; whoso bringeth ransom, let him bear away the dead,
if verily with full purpose of heart the Olympian himself so biddeth." On this wise amid the gathering of the ships mother and son spake many winged words one to the other, but the son of Cronos sent forth Iris to sacred Ilios:"Up, go, swift Iris; leave thou the abode of Olympus
and bear tidings within Ilios unto great-hearted PriamPriam that he go to the ships of the Achaeans to ransom his dear son, and that he bear giftspositive unto AchillesAchilles which shall make glad his heart; alone let him go, neither let any man beside of the Trojans go with him. A herald may attend him, an elder man,
to guide the mules and the light-running waggon, and to carry back to the city the dead, even him that AchillesAchilles slew. Let not death be in his thoughts. neither any fear; such a guide will we give him, even Argeiphontes, who shall lead him, until in his leading he bring him nigh to AchillesAchilles.
And when he shall have led him into the hut, neither shall AchillesAchilles himself slay him nor suffer any other to slay; for not without wisdom is he, neither without purpose, nor yet hardened in sin; nay, with all kindliness will he spare a suppliant man."
So spake he, and storm-footed Iris hasted to bear his message.
She came to the house of PriamPriam, and found therein clamour and wailingnegative. His sons sat about their father within the court sullying their garments with their tears, and in their midst was the old king close-wrapped in his mantle; and upon the old man's head and neck was filth in abundancenegative,
which he had gathered in his hands as he grovelled on the earth. And his daughters and his sons' wives were wailing throughout the housenegative, bethinking them of the warriors many and valiant who were lying low, slain by the hands of the Argives. And the messenger of Zeus drew nigh to PriamPriam, and spake to him;
softly she uttered her voice, yet trembling gat hold of his himbs:"Be of good courage, O Priam, son of DardanusPriam, and fear thou not at all. Not to forbode any evil to thee am I come hither, but with good intent. I am a messenger to thee from ZeusGods, who far away though he be, hath exceeding care for thee and pity.
The Olympian biddeth thee ransom goodly HectorHector, and bear gifts topositive AchillesAchilles which shall make glad his heart; alone do thou go, neither let any man beside of the Trojans go with thee. A herald may attend thee, an elder man, to guide the mules and the light-running waggon,
and to carry back to the city the dead, even him that AchillesAchilles slew. Let not death be in thy thoughts, neither any fear; such a guide shall go with thee, even Argeiphontes, who shall lead thee, until in his heading he bring thee nigh to AchillesAchilles. And when he shall have led thee into the hut,
neither shall AchillesAchilles himself slay thee nor suffer any other to slay; for not without wisdom is he, neither without purpose, nor yet hardened in sin; nay, with all kindliness will he spare a suppliant man." When she had thus spoken swift-footed Iris departed; but the king bade his sons
make ready the running mule waggon, and bind the wicker box thereon. And himself he went down to the vaulted treasure-chamberpositive, fragrant of cedar wood and high of roof, that held jewels full many: and he called to him Hecabe his wife, and spake:"Lady, from ZeusGods hath an Olympian messenger come to me,
that I go to the ships of the Achaeans to ransom my dear son, and that I bear gifts to AchillesAchilles which shall make glad his heart. But come, tell me this, how seemeth it to thy mind? For as touching mine own self, wondrously doth the desire of my heart bid me go thither to the ships, into the wide camp of the Achaeans."

So spake he, but his wife uttered a shrill cry, and spake in answernegative:"Ah, woe is me, whither now is gone the wisdom for the which of old thou wast famed among stranger folk and among them thou rulest? How art thou fain to go alone to the ships of the Achaeans to meet the eyes of the man who
hath slain thy sons, many and valiant? Of iron verily is thy heart. For if so be he get thee in his power and his eyes behold thee, so savage and faithless is the man, he will neither pity thee nor anywise have reverence. Nay, let us now make our lament afar from him we mourn, abiding here in the hall. On this wise for him did mighty Fate spin
with her thread at his birth, when myself did bear him, that he should glut swift-footed dogs far from his parents, in the abode of a violent man, in whose inmost heart I were fain to fix my teeth and feed thereon; then haply might deeds of requital be wrought for my son, seeing in no wise while playing the dastard was he slain of him,
but while standing forth in defence of the men and deep-bosomed women of Troy, with no thought of shelter or of flight." Then in answer spake unto her the old manpositive, god-like PriamPriam:"Seek not to stay me that am fain to go, neither be thyself a bird of ill-boding in my halls; thou shalt not persuade me.
For if any other of the men that are upon the face of the earth had bidden me this, whether of seers that divine from sacrifice or of priests, a false thing might we deem it, and turn away therefrom the more; but now—for myself I heard the voice of the goddess and looked upon her face—I will go forth, neither shall her word be vain. And if it be my fate
to lie dead by the ships of the brazen-coated Achaeans, so would I have it; forthwith let AchillesAchilles slay me, when once I have clasped in my arms my son, and have put from me the desire for wailingnegative."
He spake, and opened the goodly lids of chests, wherefrom he took twelve beauteous robes
and twelve cloaks of single fold, and as many coverlets, and as many white mantles, and therewithal as many tunics. And of gold he weighed out and bare forth talents, ten in all, and two gleaming tripods, and four cauldrons, and a cup exceeding fair, that the men of Thrace had given him
when he went thither on an embassage, a great treasure; not even this did the old man spare in his halls, for he was exceeding fain to ransom his dear son.negative Then drave he all the Trojans from out the portico, and chid them with words of reviling:"Get ye hence, wretches, ye that work me shame!
Have ye not also lamentation at home, that ye come hither to vex me? Count ye it not enough that Zeus, son of CronosGods, hath brought this sorrow upon me, that I should lose my son the best of all? Nay, but yourselves too shall know it, for easier shall ye be, now he is dead, for the Achaeans to slay.
But for me, or ever mine eyes behold the city sacked and laid waste, may I go down into the house of HadesGods." He spake, and plying his staff went among the men, and they went forth from before the old man in his haste. Then called he aloud to his sons, chiding Helenus and Paris and goodly Agathon
and Pammon and Antiphonus and Polites, good at the war-cry, and Deiphobus and Hippothous and lordly Dius. To these nine the old man called aloud, and gave command:"Haste ye, base children that are my shame; would that ye all together in HectorHector's stead had been slain at the swift ships!
Woe is me, that am all unblest, seeing that I begat sons the best in the broad land of Troy, yet of them I avow that not one is left, not godlike Nestor, not Troilus the warrior charioteer, not HectorHector that was a god among men, neither seemed he as the son of a mortal man, but of a god:
all them hath Ares slain, yet these things of shame are all left me, false of tongue, nimble of foot, peerless at beating the floor in the dance, robbers of lambs and kids from your own folk. Will ye not make me ready a waggon, and that with speed, and lay all these things therein, that we may get forward on our way?positive"

And the old man, godlike PriamPriam, answered him: "If thou art indeed a squire of Achilles, Peleus' sonAchilles come now, tell me all the truth, whether my sonHector is even yet by the ships or whether by now AchillesAchilles hath hewn him limb from limb and cast him before his dogs.negative"
Then again the messenger Argeiphontes spake to him:"Old sire, not yet have dogs and birds devoured him, but still he lieth there beside the ship of AchillesAchilles amid the huts as he was at the first; and this is now the twelfth day that he lieth there, yet his flesh decayeth not at all,
neither do worms consume it, such as devour men that be slain in fightnegative. Truly AchillesAchilles draggeth him ruthlessly about the barrow of Patroclus his dear comradePatroclusnegative, so oft as sacred DawnGods appeareth, howbeit he marreth him not; thou wouldst thyself marvel, wert thou to come and see how dewy-fresh he lieth, and is washen clean of blood,positive
neither hath anywhere pollution; and all the wounds are closed wherewith he was stricken, for many there were that drave the bronze into his flesh.positive In such wise do the blessed godsHector care for thy sonHector, a corpse though he be, seeing he was dear unto theirGods hearts.positive" So spake he, and the old manPriam waxed gladrelief, and answered, saying:
"My child, a good thing is it in sooth e'en to give to the immortals such gifts as be due; for never did my son—as sure as ever such a one there was—forget in our halls the gods that hold Olympus; wherefore they have remembered this for him, even though he be in the doom of death. But come, take thou from me this fair gobletpositive,
and guard me myself, and guide me with the speeding of the gods, until I be come unto the hut of the Achilles son of Pe1eusAchilles." And again the messenger, Argeiphontes, spake to him:"Thou dost make trial of me, old sire, that am younger than thou; but thou shalt not prevail upon me, seeing thou biddest me take gifts from thee while AchillesAchilles knoweth naught thereof.
Of him have I fear and awe at heart, that I should defraud him, lest haply some evil befall me hereafter.fear Howbeit as thy guide would I go even unto glorious Argos, attending thee with kindly care in a swift ship or on foot; nor would any man make light of thy guide and set upon thee."

So spake the Helper, and leaping upon the chariot behind the horses quickly grasped in his hands the lash and reins, and breathed great might into the horses and mules. But when they were come to the walls and the trench that guarded the ships, even as the watchers were but now busying them about their supper,
upon all of these the messenger Argeiphontes shed sleep, and forthwith opened the gates, and thrust back the bars, and brought within Priam, and the splendid gifts upon the wainpositive. But when they were come to the hut of Achilles Peleus' sonAchilles, the lofty hut which the Myrmidons had builded for their king,
hewing therefor beams of fir —and they had roofed it over with downy thatch, gathered from the meadows; and round it they reared for him, their king, a great court with thick-set pales; and the door thereof was held by one single bar of fir that
three Achaeans were wont to drive home, and three to draw back the great bolt of the door （three of the rest, but AchillesAchilles would drive it home even of himself）—then verily the helper HermesGods opened the door for the old man, and brought in the glorious gifts for the Achilles swift-footed son of PeleusAchilles; and from the chariot he stepped down to the ground and spake, saying:
"Old sire, I that am come to thee am immortal god, even HermesGods; for the FatherGods sent me to guide thee on thy way. But now verily will I go back, neither come within AchillesAchilles' sight; good cause for wrath would it be that an immortal god should thus openly be entertained of mortals.
But go thou in, and clasp the knees of the Achilles, son of PeleusAchilles and entreat him by his father and his fair-haired mother and his child, that thou mayest stir his soul."positive
So spake HermesGods, and departed unto high Olympus; and PriamPriam leapt from his chariot to the ground,
and left there Idaeus, who abode holding the horses and mules; but the old manPriam went straight toward the house where Achilles, dear to ZeusAchilles, was wont to sit.positive Therein he found AchillesAchilles>, but his comrades sat apart: two only, the warrior Automedon and Alcimus, scion of AresGods,
waited busily upon him; and he was newly ceased from meat, even from eating and drinking, and the table yet stood by his sidenegative. Unseen of these great Priam Priamentered in, and coming close to AchillesAchilles, clasped in his hands his knees, and kissed his hands, the terrible, man-slaying hands that had slain his many sons.fearpositive
And as when sore blindness of heart cometh upon a man, that in his own country slayeth another and escapeth to a land of strangers, to the house of some man of substance, and wonder holdeth them that look upon him; even so was AchillesAchilles seized with wonderwonder at sight of godlike PriamPriam, and seized with wonder were the others likewisewonder, and they glanced one at the other.
But Priam made entreaty, and spake to him, saying: "Remember thy father, O Achilles like to the godsAchilles, whose years are even as mine, on the grievous threshold of old age. Him full likely the dwellers that be round about are entreating evilly, neither is there any to ward from him ruin and bane.
Howbeit, while he heareth of thee as yet alive he hath joy at heart, and therewithal hopeth day by day that he shall see his dear son returning from Troy-land. But I—I am utterly unblest, seeing I begat sons the best in the broad land of Troy, yet of them I avow that not one is left.
Fifty I had, when the sons of the Achaeans came; nineteen were born to me of the self-same womb, and the others women of the palace bare. Of these, many as they were, furious AresGods hath loosed the knees, and he that alone was left me, that by himself guarded the city and the men,
him thou slewest but now as he fought for his country, even Hector.Hector positive For his sake am I now come to the ships of the Achaeans to win him back from thee, and I bear with me ransom past counting. Nay, have thou awe of the gods, AchillesAchilles, and positivetake pity on me, remembering thine own father. Lo, I am more piteous far than he,
and have endured what no other mortal on the face of earth hath yet endured, to reach forth my hand to the face of him that hath slain my sons."positive
So spake he, and in AchillesAchilles"> he roused desire to weep for his fatherlament; and he took the old manPriam by the hand, and gently put him from him. So the twain bethought them of their dead, and wept; the one for man-slaying HectorHector wept sore,
the while he grovelled at AchillesAchilles' feet, but AchillesAchilles wept for his own fatherlament, and now again for Patroclus Patrocluslament; and the sound of their moaning went up through the house. But when goodly AchillesAchilles had had his fill of lamenting, and the longing therefor had departed from his heart and limbs,
forthwith then he sprang from his seat, and raised the old man by his hand, pitying his hoary head and hoary beard; and he spake and addressed him with winged words:"positive Ah, unhappy man, full many in good sooth are the evils thou hast endured in thy soul. How hadst thou the heart to come alone to the ships of the Achaeans,
to meet the eyes of me that have slain thy sons many and valiant? Of iron verily is thy heart. But come, sit thou upon a seat, and our sorrows will we suffer to lie quiet in our hearts, despite our pain; for no profit cometh of chill lament.positive
For on this wise have the gods spun the thread for wretched mortals, that they should live in pain; and themselves are sorrowless. For two urns are set upon the floor of ZeusGods of gifts that he giveth, the one of ills, the other of blessings. To whomsoever Zeus, that hurleth the thunderbolt,Gods giveth a mingled lot,
that man meeteth now with evil, now with good; but to whomsoever he giveth but of the baneful, him he maketh to be reviled of man, and direful madness driveth him over the face of the sacred earth, and he wandereth honoured neither of gods nor mortals.negative Even so unto Peleus did the gods give glorious gifts
from his birth; for he excelled all men in good estate and in wealth, and was king over the Myrmidons, and to him that was but a mortal the gods gave a goddess to be his wife.
Howbeit even upon him the gods brought evil, in that there nowise sprang up in his halls offspring of princely sons, but he begat one only son, doomed to an untimely fate. Neither may I tend him as he groweth old, seeing that far, far from mine own country I abide in the land of Troy, vexing thee and thy children. And of thee, old sire, we hear that of old thou wast blestpositive; how of all that toward the sea Lesbos, the seat of Macar, encloseth,
and Phrygia in the upland, and the boundless Hellespont, over all these folk, men say, thou, old sire, wast preeminent by reason of thy wealth and thy sons. Howbeit from the time when the heavenly gods brought upon thee this bane, ever around thy city are battles and slayings of men. Bear thou up, neither wail ever ceaselessly in thy heart; for naught wilt thou avail by grieving for thy son,
neither wilt thou bring him back to lifelamentpositive; ere that shalt thou suffer some other ill."
And the old man, godlike PriamPriam, answered him:positive "Seat me not anywise upon a chair, O Achilles thou fostered of ZeusAchilles, so long as HectorHector lieth uncared-for amid the hutsnegative;
nay, give him back with speed, that mine eyes may behold him; and do thou accept the ransom, the great ransom, that we bring. So mayest thou have joy thereof, and come to thy native land, seeing that from the first thou hast spared me.positive" Then with an angry glance from beneath his brows spake to himAchillesAchilles swift of foot:negative
"Provoke me no more, old sir; I am minded even of myself to give HectorHector back to thee; >>>>>>> fe9cb1715465256b0366eb238d50024609697b43 for from ZeusGods there came to me a messenger, even the mother that bare meGods, daughter of the old man of the seaGods. And of thee, PriamPriam, do I know in my heart—it nowise escapeth me—that some god led thee to the swift ships of the Achaeans.
For no mortal man, were he never so young and strong, would dare to come amid the host; neither could he then escape the watch, nor easily thrust back the bar of our doors. Wherefore now stir my heart no more amid my sorrows, lest, old sire, I spare not even thee within the huts,
my suppliant though thou art, and so sin against the behest of ZeusGods." So spake he, and the old man was seized with fear, and hearkened to his wordfear. But like a lion the son of PeleusAchilles sprang forth from the houses—not alone, for with him went two squires as well, even the warrior Automedon and Alcimus,
they that AchillesAchilles honoured above all his comrades, after the dead Patroclus Patroclus. These then loosed from beneath the yoke the horses and mules, and led within the herald, the crier of the old king, and set him on a chair;negative and from the wain of goodly felloes they took the countless ransom for Hector's head.
But they left there two robes and a fair-woven tunic, to the end that AchillesAchilles might enwrap the dead therein and so give him to be borne to his homepositive. Then AchillesAchilles called forth the hand-maids and bade them wash and anoint him, bearing him to a place apart that PriamPriam might not have sight of his son, lest in grief of heart he should not restrain his wrath,
whenso he had sight of his son, and AchillesAchilles' own spirit be stirred to anger, and he slay him, and so sin against the behest of Zeus. So when the handmaids had washed the body and anointed it with oil, and had cast about it a fair cloak and a tunic, then AchillesAchilles himself lifted it and set it upon a bier,
and his comrades with him lifted it upon the polished waggon. Then he uttered a groan, and called by name upon his dear comrade:"Be not thou wroth with me, Patroclus Patroclus, if thou hearest even in the house of Hades that I have given back goodly Hector to his dear father, seeing that not unseemly is the ransom he hath given me.
And unto thee shall I render even of this all that is thy due."positive
So spake goodly AchillesAchilles, and went back within the hut and on the richly-wrought chair wherefrom he had risen sate him down by the opposite wall, and he spake unto PriamPriam, saying:"Thy son, old sire, is given back according to thy wish,
and lieth upon a bier; and at break of day thou shalt thyself behold him, as thou bearest him hence; but for this present let us bethink us of supper. For even the fair-haired Niobe bethought her of meat, albeit twelve children perished in her halls, six daughters and six lusty sons.
The sons ApolloGods slew with shafts from his silver bow, being wroth against Niobe, and the daughters the archer ArtemisGods, for that Niobe had matched her with fair-cheeked LetoGods, saying that the goddess had borne but twain, while herself was mother to many; wherefore they, for all they were but twain, destroyed them all.
For nine days' space they lay in their blood, nor was there any to bury them, for the son of Cronos turned the folk to stones; howbeit on the tenth day the gods of heaven buried them; and Niobe bethought her of meat, for she was wearied with the shedding of tears. And now somewhere amid the rocks, on the lonely mountains,
on Sipylus, where, men say, are the couching-places of goddesses, even of the nymphs that range swiftly in the dance about Achelous, there, albeit a stone, she broodeth over her woes sent by the gods. But come, let us twain likewise, noble old sire, bethink us of meat; and thereafter shalt thou make lament over thy dear son,
when thou hast borne him into Ilios; mourned shall he be of thee many tears."lamentpositive Therewith swift AchillesAchilles sprang up, and slew a white-fleeced sheep, and his comrades flayed it and made it ready well and duly, and sliced it cunningly and spitted the morsels, and roasted them carefully and drew all off the spits.
And Automedon took bread and dealt it forth on the table in fair baskets, while AchillesAchilles dealt the meat. So they put forth their hands to the good cheer lying ready before them.positive But when they had put from them the desire of food and drink, then verily Priam, son of DardanusPriam, marvelled at AchillesAchilles, how tall he was and how comely;
for he was like the gods to look upon. And a son of Dardanus, did AchillesAchilles marvel, beholding his goodly aspect and hearkening to his words. But when they had had their fill of gazing one upon the other, then the old man, godlike PriamPriam, was first to speak, saying:
"Show me now my bed with speed, O thou nurtured of ZeusAchilles, that lulled at length by sweet sleep we may rest and take our joy; for never yet have mine eyes closed beneath mine eyelids since at thy hands my son lost his life, but ever do I wail and brood over my countless sorrows,
grovelling in the filth in the closed spaces of the court. But now have I tasted of meat, and have let flaming wine pass down my throat; whereas till now had I tasted naught."
He spake, and AchillesAchilles bade his comrades and the handmaids set bedsteads beneath the portico,
and to lay on them fair purple blankets, and to spread thereover coverlets, and on these to put fleecy cloaks for clothing. So the maids went forth from the hall with torches in their hands, and straightway spread two beds in busy hastepositive. Then mockingly spake unto PriamPriam Achilles, swift of footAchilles:
"Without do thou lay thee down, dear old sire, lest there come hither one of the counsellors of the Achaeans, that ever sit by my side and take counsel, as is meet. If one of these were to have sight of thee through the swift black night, forthwith might he haply tell it to Agamemnon, shepherd of the hostAgamemnon,
and so should there arise delay in the giving back of the body. But come, tell me this, and declare it truly: for how many days' space thou art minded to make funeral for goodly HectorHector, to the end that for so long I may myself abide, and may keep back the host." And the old man, godlike PriamPriam, answered him: saying:
"If thou indeed art willing that I accomplish for goodly Hector his burial, then in doing on this wise, O AchillesAchilles, wilt thou do according to my wish. Thou knowest how we are pent within the city, and far is it to fetch wood from the mountain, and the Trojans are sore afraid.
For nine days' space will we wail for him in our halls, and on the tenth will we make his funeral, and the folk shall feast, and on the eleventh will we heap a barrow over him, and on the twelfth will we do battle, if so be we must.positive" Then spake to him in answer swift-footed, goodly AchillesAchilles:"Thus shall this also be aged Priam, even as thou wouldest have it;
for I will hold back the battle for such time as thou dost bid.positive" When he had thus spoken he clasped the old man's right hand by the wrist, lest his heart should any wise wax fearful. So they laid them to sleep there in the fore-hall of the house, the herald and PriamPriam, with hearts of wisdom in their breasts;
but AchillesAchilles slept in the innermost part of the well-builded hut, and by his side lay fair-cheeked Briseis.
Now all the other gods and men, lords of chariots, slumbered the whole night through, overcome of soft sleep; but not upon the helper HermesGods might sleep lay hold,
as he pondered in mind how he should guide king PriamPriam forth from the ships unmarked of the strong keepers of the gate. He took his stand above his head and spake to him, saying:"Old sire, no thought then hast thou of any evil, that thou still sleepest thus amid foemen, for that AchillesAchilles has spared thee.
Now verily hast thou ransomed thy son, and a great price thou gavest. But for thine own life must the sons thou hast, they that be left behind, give ransorn thrice so great, if so be Agamemnon, Atreus' son, have knowledge of thee, or the host of the Achaeans have knowledge." So spake he, and the old man was seized with fearfear, and made the herald to arise.
And HermesGods yoked for them the horses and mules, and himself lightly drave them through the camp, neither had any man knowledge thereof.positive But when they were now come to the ford of the fair-flowing river, even eddying Xanthus, that immortal ZeusGods begat, then HermesGods departed to high Olympus,
and DawnGods, the saffron-robed, was spreading over the face of all the earth. So they with moaning and wailing drave the horses to the city, and the mules bare the dead.positive Neither was any other ware of them, whether man or fair-girdled woman; but in truth Cassandra, peer of golden Aphrodite,
having gone up upon Pergamus, marked her dear father as he stood in the car, and the herald, the city's crier; and she had sight of that other lying on the bier in the waggon drawn of the mules. Thereat she uttered a shrill cry, and called throughout all the town:"Come ye, men and women of Troy, and behold Hector,
if ever while yet he lived ye had joy of his coming back from battle; since great joy was he to the city and to all the folk."
So spake she, nor was any man left there within the city, neither any woman, for upon all had come grief that might not be borne; and hard by the gates they met PriamPriam, as he bare home the dead.
First Hector's dear wife and queenly mother flung themselves upon the light-running waggon, and clasping his head the while, wailed and tore their hair; and the folk thronged about and wept. And now the whole day long until set of sun had they made lament for Hector with shedding of tears there without the gates,
had not the old man spoken amid the folk from out the car:"Make me way for the mules to pass through; thereafter shall ye take your fill of wailing, when I have brought him to the house." So spake he, and they stood apart and made way for the waggon. But the others, when they had brought him to the glorious house,
laid him on a corded bedstead, and by his side set singers, leaders of the dirge, who led the song of lamentation—they chanted the dirge, and thereat the women made lament. And amid these white-armed Andromache led the wailing,lament holding in her arms the while the head of man-slaying HectorHector:
"Husband, perished from out of life art thou, yet in thy youth, and leavest me a widow in thy halls; and thy son is still but a babe, the son born of thee and me in our haplessness; neither do I deem that he will come to manhood, for ere that shall this city be wasted utterly.lamentpositive. For thou hast perished that didst watch thereover,
thou that didst guard it, and keep safe its noble wives and little children. These, I ween, shall soon be riding upon the hollow ships, and I among them; and thou, my child, shalt follow with me to a place where thou shalt labour at unseemly tasks, toiling before the face of some ungentle master, or else some Achaean shall seize thee by the arm
and hurl thee from the wall, a woeful death,lament being wroth for that HectorHector slew his brother haply, or his father, or his son, seeing that full many Achaeans at the hands of HectorHector have bitten the vast earth with their teeth; for nowise gentle was thy father in woeful war.
Therefore the folk wail for him throughout the city, and grief unspeakable and sorrow hast thou brought upon thy parents, HectorHector; and for me beyond all others shall grievous woes be left. For at thy death thou didst neither stretch out thy hands to me from thy bed, nor speak to me any word of wisdom whereon
I might have pondered night and day with shedding of tears."
So spake she wailing, and thereat the women made lament. And among them Hecabe in turns led the vehement wailing:"HectorHector, far dearest to my heart of all my children, lo, when thou livedst thou wast dear to the gods,
and therefore have they had care of thee for all thou art in the doom of death. For of other sons of mine whomsoever he took would swift-footed AchillesAchilles sell beyond the unresting sea, unto Samos and Imbros and Lemnos, shrouded in smoke, but, when from thee he had taken away thy life with the long-edged bronze
oft would he drag thee about the barrow of his comrade, Patroclus Patroclus, whom thou didst slay; howbeit even so might he not raise him up. all dewy-fresh thou liest in my halls as wert thou g newly slain, like as one whom Apollo of the silver bow assaileth with his gentle shafts and slayeth."
So spake she wailing, and roused unabating lamentpositive. And thereafter Helen was the third to lead the wailing:lament"HectorHector, far dearest to my heart of all my husband's brethren! In sooth my husband is godlike Alexander, that brought me to Troy-land —would I died ere then!
For this is now the twentieth year from the time when I went from thence and am gone from my native land, but never yet heard I evil or despiteful word from thee; nay, if so be any other spake reproachfully of me in the halls, a brother of thine or a sister, or brother's fair-robed wife,
or thy mother—but thy father was ever gentle as he had been mine own—yet wouldst thou turn them with speech and restrain them by the gentleness of thy spirit and thy gentle words. Wherefore I wail alike for thee and for my hapless self with grief at heart; for no longer have I anyone beside in broad Troy
that is gentle to me or kind; but all men shudder at me."
So spake she wailing, and thereat the countless throng made moan. But the old man PriamPriam spake among the folk, saying:"Bring wood now, ye men of Troy, unto the city, neither have ye anywise fear at heart of a cunning ambush of the Argivespositive; for verily AchillesAchilles laid upon me this word
when he sent me forth from the black ships, that he would do us no hurt until the twelfth dawn be come." So spake he, and they yoked oxen and mules to waggons, and speedily thereafter gathered together before the city. For nine days' space they brought in measureless store of wood,
but when the tenth Dawn arose, giving light unto mortals, then bare they forth bold HectorHector, shedding tears the while, and on the topmost pyre they laid the dead man, and cast fire thereon.positive But soon as early Dawn appeared, the rosy-fingeredGods, then gathered the folk about the pyre of glorious HectorHector.
And when they were assembled and met together, first they quenched with flaming wine all the pyre, so far as the fire's might had come upon it, and thereafter his brethren and his comrades gathered the white bones, mourning, and big tears flowed ever down their cheeks.
The bones they took and placed in a golden urn, covering them over with soft purple robes, and quickly laid the urn in a hollow grave, and covered it over with great close-set stones. positiveThen with spe'[ed heaped they the mound, and round about were watchers set on every side,
lest the well-greaved Achaeans should set upon them before the time. And when they had piled the barrow they went back, and gathering together duly feasted a glorious feast in the palace positive of Priam, the king fostered of PriamZeusGods On this wise held they funeral for horse-taming HectorHector.positive